Guide to the First National Bank of Missoula Records 1866-1965
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
First National Bank of Missoula Records
1866-1965
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 107
First National Bank of Missoula
28.0 linear feet 6 archival boxes and 86 oversize volumes
This collection contains financial, organizational, correspondence, promotional, and reference materials generated by the First National Bank of Missoula, Montana, and a small sample of financial records from the Missoula Trust and Savings Bank.
Historical Note
The First National Bank was organized in 1873 in Missoula, Montana, under the name Missoula National Bank. The bank was not only one of the first businesses in Missoula, but one of the first banks in Montana Territory. Bank officers included Christopher Higgins, Francis L. Worden, and J. P.Reinhard.
Within a few months of its creation, the bank survived the Panic of 1873, which forced 172 banks across the United States to liquidate. During the last decades of the nineteenth century the Missoula bank played an important role in the gold trade in western Montana. It acted as the middleman in transferring the gold from the prospectors to the large financial institutions of the east coast. All of these gold transactions enabled the Missoula bank to obtain more currency, which was important to the growth of the Missoula and western Montana economy.
In 1889, the bank became the First National Bank of Missoula. By 1976, it changed its name to First National Montana Bank of Missoula. By 1986, it was First Interstate Bank.
The Missoula Trust and Savings Bank was incorporated in 1903. Officers were Frederick D. Whisler, President; Dr. Oel. S. Misick, Vice President; and John W. Hicklin, Cashier. Its charter expired in 1953.
This collection contains financial, organizational, correspondence, promotional, and reference materials generated by the First National Bank of Missoula and a small sample of financial records from the Missoula Trust and Savings Bank. Collection materials significantly document Missoula's early economic history, the town's foundational business relationships, the ebb and flow of western Montana economic development from the late nineteenth century through the early twentieth century, the impacts of national procedural/regulatory changes upon rural banks, and daily operations at the Missoula institution.
The collection is arranged in five series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1.75 linear feet, 1873-1965
Series II: Organization, 1 folder, 1866-1913
Series III: Financial Records, 1.0 linear feet and 81 oversize volumes, 1873-1965
Series IV: Scrapbooks and Printed Materials, 2.25 linear feet, 1903-1964
Series V: Missoula Trust and Savings Bank, 1 folder and 5 oversize volumes, 1914-1929
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The records were in the possession of the First National Montana Bank of Missoula until time of donation to the Archives.
Gift of David R. Calahan of the First National Montana Bank of Missoula, 1982.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Missoula National Bank; Missoula Trust and Savings Bank
Missoula (Mont.)--Economic conditions
Banks and banking--Montana--Missoula
Montana; Labor History
- Correspondence, 1873-1965; Series I; 1.75 linear feet
  This series contains outgoing and incoming correspondence regarding First National Bank operations. Correspondence sequences are relatively complete from 1873 to 1900; however, significant gaps exist after 1900 and the sequence ends in 1921. This series also includes one file of correspondence with K. Ross Toole, dated 1965. This file documents K. Ross Toole's efforts to secure the collection for the Archives, an instructional essay written by Toole regarding archival processing in Montana, and transcriptions of letters from the S.T. Hauser collection at the Montana State Historical Society he deemed relevant to the First National Bank collection.
  - Outgoing Correspondence, August 1873 - June 1875 (Box-volume 1/1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, June 1875 - November 1876 (Box-volume 1/2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, August 1879 - December 1880 (Box-volume 2/3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, December 1880 - December 1881 (Box-volume 2/4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, December 1895 - January 1900 (Box-volume 3/5)
  - Correspondence, 1889 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1892 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1896 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Correspondence, 1897-1902 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Correspondence, 1902 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Correspondence, 1902, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Mid - Mik, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Mil, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Mim - Mis, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Mit - Miz, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Moa - Mol, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Mom - Mon, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Moo - Mop, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Mora - Morp, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Morr - Morz, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Mos - Mot, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Mou - Moz, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Mua - Muk, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Mul, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Murphy, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Mur, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Mus, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Correspondence, 1921 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Toole, K. Ross, 1965 (Box-folder 4/4)
- Organization, 1866-1913; Series II; 1 folder
  This series contains three documents relating to the incorporation of the First National Bank. Included is a copy of the 1866 Articles of Incorporation for the First National Bank of Helena, Montana (used as a template for the Missoula National Bank's articles of incorporation), a copy of the 1873 Articles of Incorporation for the Missoula National Bank, and a 1913 amendment to the First Nationa Montana Bank of Missoula's Articles of Incorporation. These materials document the early organization of one of western Montana's first corporate ventures.
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1866-1913 (Box-folder 4/5)
- Financial Records, 1873-1965; Series III; 1.0 linear feet and 81 oversize volumes
  This series contains financial records from the First National Bank, primarily bound ledgers. Materials include general operating ledgers, individual account records, daily balance logs, regulatory reports of assets and liabilities, cash and credit transaction documents, and client signature books. Federal records include reports to and notices from the U.S. Treasury Department. Materials in this series present significant documentation of Missoula's early economic history, the town's foundational business relationships, the ebb and flow of western Montana economic development from the late nineteenth century through the early twentieth century, the impacts of national procedural/regulatory changes upon rural banks, and daily operations at the Missoula institution.
  - Reports of Condition, 1879-1909 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - U.S. Treasury, Reports and Notices, 1879-1933 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Cancelled Checks, J.S. Chamberlain, 1888 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Account Ledger Sheet, J.S. Chamberlain, 1889 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Account Ledger, 1965 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Journal, 1885-1908 (Box-volume 4/6)
  - General Ledger, July 1873 - October 1881 (Volume 7)
  - General Ledger, November 1881 - September 1885 (Volume 8)
  - General Ledger, October 1885 - July 1889 (Volume 9)
  - General Ledger, July 1889 - October 1896 (Volume 10)
  - General Ledger, November 1896 - December 1898 (Volume 11)
  - General Ledger, January 1899 - March 1899 (Volume 12)
  - General Ledger, March 1899 - June 1902 (Volume 13)
  - General Ledger, June 1902 - March 1906 (Volume 14)
  - General Ledger, March 1906 - May 1908 (Volume 15)
  - General Ledger, May 1908 - December 1910 (Volume 16)
  - General Ledger, December 1912 - September 1915 (Volume 17)
  - General Ledger, September 1915 - March 1918 (Volume 18)
  - General Ledger, March 1918 - December 1919 (Volume 19)
  - General Ledger, January 1920 - December 1921 (Volume 20)
  - General Ledger, January 1922 - December 1923 (Volume 21)
  - General Ledger, January 1924 - December 1926 (Volume 22)
  - General Ledger, January 1927 - December 1927 (Volume 23)
  - General Balances, December 1876 - December 1881 (Volume 24)
  - General Balances, October 1892 - January 1895 (Volume 25)
  - General Balances, March 1906 - June 1908 (Volume 26)
  - General Balances, June 1908 - October 1910 (Volume 27)
  - General Balances, October 1910 - February 1913 (Volume 28)
  - General Balances, February 1913 - June 1915 (Volume 29)
  - General Balances, June 1915 - September 1917 (Volume 30)
  - General Balances, October 1917 - December 1919 (Volume 31)
  - General Balances, January 1920 - June 1923 (Volume 32)
  - General Balances, November 1926 - April 1930 (Volume 33)
  - General Balances, April 1930 - September 1933 (Volume 34)
  - General Balances, September 1933 - March 1937 (Volume 35)
  - General Balances, September 1933 - March 1937 (Volume 36)
  - General Balances, September 1933 - March 1937 (Volume 37)
  - General Balances, April 1945 - November 1949 (Volume 38)
  - Cash Book, 1873-1877 (Volume 39)
  - Counter Cash, 1882-1885 (Volume 40)
  - Loan Journal, 1873-1878 (Volume 41)
  - Loans and Renewals, 1911-1917 (Volume 42)
  - Liability Ledger, 1908-1915 (Volume 43)
  - Bond Register, 1915-1940 (Volume 44)
  - Certificate Register, 1887-1902 (Volume 45)
  - Collection Register, 1885-1889 (Volume 46)
  - Certificate Register, 1903-1915 (Volume 47)
  - Demand Certificates, 1891-1891 (Volume 48)
  - Discount Register, 1906-1909 (Volume 49)
  - Draft Register, 1892-1955 (Volume 50)
  - Exchange Record, 1891-1891 (Volume 51)
  - Signature Book, 1873-1888 (Box-volume 4/52)
  - Signature Book, 1888-1892 (Box-volume 5/53)
  - Individual Ledger, July 1873 - December 1884 (Volume 54)
  - Individual Ledger, January 1885 - March 1888 (Volume 55)
  - Individual Ledger, March 1888 - September 1891 (Volume 56)
  - Individual Ledger, September 1891 - June 1894 (Volume 57)
  - Individual Ledger, July 1894 - December 1896 (Volume 58)
  - Individual Ledger, January 1897 - December 1898 (Volume 59)
  - Individual Ledger, January 1899 - May 1900 (Volume 60)
  - Individual Ledger, June 1900 - June 1901 (Volume 61)
  - Individual Ledger, A - K, July 1901 - December 1902 (Volume 62)
  - Individual Ledger, A - K, January 1903 - June 1904 (Volume 63)
  - Individual Ledger, A - G, July 1904 - December 1905 (Volume 64)
  - Individual Ledger, A - E, April 1907 - August 1908 (Volume 65)
  - Individual Ledger, R - Z, August 1908 - April 1910 (Volume 67)
  - Individual Ledger, R - Z, May 1910 - June 1912 (Volume 68)
  - Individual Ledger, E - K, July 1912 - April 1914 (Volume 69)
  - Capital Stock and Surplus Ledger, 1928-1948 (Volume 70)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, July 1873 - March 1882 (Volume 71)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, April 1882 - December 1884 (Volume 72)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, January 1885 - July 1887 (Volume 73)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, August 1887 - May 1889 (Volume 74)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, June 1889 - December 1890 (Volume 75)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, January 1891 - April 1892 (Volume 76)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, May 1892 - August 1893 (Volume 77)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, September 1893 - June 1895 (Volume 78)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, July 1901 - April 1903 (Volume 79)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, May 1903 - June 1904 (Volume 80)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, July 1904 - March 1906 (Volume 81)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, April 1906 - March 1907 (Volume 82)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, April 1907 - May 1907 (Volume 83)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, May 1907 - January 1908 (Volume 84)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, February 1908 - January 1909 (Volume 85)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, February 1909 - December 1909 (Volume 86)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, January 1910 - March 1911 (Volume 87)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, April 1911 - September 1912 (Volume 88)
  - Individual Balance Ledger, September 1912 - April 1914 (Volume 89)
  - Individual Statements of Account, 1880-1890 (Box-volume 5/90)
- Scrapbooks and Printed Materials, 1903-1964; Series IV; 2.25 linear feet
  This series contains three newspaper scrapbooks detailing developments within the First National Bank from 1903-1939, samples of internal forms, and two examples of Bank promotional materials. The items in this series provide broad insights into First National Bank operations and public relations.
  - Blank Checks, undated (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Promotional Flyer, undated (Box-folder 5/2)
  - 1903-1918 (Box-folder OS6/1)
  - 1909-1917 (Box-folder OS6/2)
  - 1917-1939 (Box-folder OS6/3)
  - Blank Ledger Sheets, undated (Box-folder OS6/4)
  - Promotional Section, Missoulian, 1964 (Box-folder OS6/5)
- Missoula Trust and Savings Bank, 1914-1929; Series V; 1 folder and 5 oversize volumes
  This series contains financial records from the Missoula Trust and Savings Bank. The exact relationship between Missoula Trust and Savings Bank and the First National Bank is not established by collection materials.
  - Safe Default Vault Certificate, 1918 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - General Ledger, 1925-1929 (Volume 91)
  - General Balance, 1923-1927 (Volume 92)
  - Deposit Ledger, 1914-1915 (Volume 93)
  - Individual Ledger, A- M, 1918-1919 (Volume 94)
  - Individual Ledger, 1917-1918 (Volume 95)